[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right everyone welcome to the stowah
i am peter limberg the steward of the
stoa and the stow is a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most at the knife's edge of this
very moment and today we
have a very special guest susan
blackmore i'm excited
for today's session um
so i'm going to hand it over to the
emcee of
today's session in a moment who is
rebecca fox
rebecca is an author of a series of
graphic novels such as murmurs of doubt
and how to be reasonable and she has an
excellent podcast called the seeker
and the skeptic and uh she's the skeptic
uh maybe being seduced to being a seeker
we'll find out um but that being said i
will uh
tag rebecca in and she will uh introduce
susan and give the protocols of uh the q
a today
so that being said rebecca hand over to
you
oop you're in uh but it sounds like
you're saying something
very interesting here we go i was just
saying hey everyone
um it's really exciting to be doing this
i'm a big
fan of susan's for many years as peter
mentioned i'm a skeptic
so the first time i encountered her work
was at a skeptic conference
and um she got up to speak about i think
it was about uh
well it's about lots of things but out
of body experiences and she talked a
little bit about her history
and what really struck me is obviously
she's quirky she's intelligent she's an
amazing speaker
but she's also very very present in a
way that's quite rare
sometimes in skeptics we're also in our
head are skeptics
it was nice to see someone on stage who
was being truly herself
which was very exciting uh so i'm hoping
this evening this afternoon this morning
for some of you
uh to talk about um the things that
we're interested in here at the stoa
and i think susan will have really
insightful things to say about most of
this stuff because she's a psychologist
she's a mimeticist and she's had
experience believing some very strange
things in her past um
she studied parapsychology she knows her
way around a lot of esoteric topics
um how this is gonna work is we're gonna
have a bit of a chat i'm gonna ask some
of the questions i've been saving up for
all these
these years as a keen reader of susan's
work and then i'm gonna let you all have
a chance to ask your own questions
and we can do that in two different ways
if you'd like to ask susan directly
then you can write a question just write
question at the top in the chat
and then question about x whatever your
question is about
and i'll call on you to come up on
screen and ask that question
or if you prefer i can read your
question for you and this is going to be
recorded on youtube so
you know if you're having a bad hair day
or any other reason you don't want to
appear on screen
you can just get me to ask questions
because my hair's looking amazing today
uh so as i was saying
i'm a long-term fan of susan's what i
really like about her what i like about
her writing
is how she comes at the questions that
she asks from
at least three different directions um
she looks at it as a psychologist and as
a scientist
she looks at it as well i don't think
you'd call yourself a philosopher susan
but you look at it in a philosophical
way
and well a thoughtful critical thinking
sort of way let's say
and then also because i never studied
the philosophy so i always feel
you know i mustn't call myself i haven't
got a philosophy degree so i yes
you mustn't call myself a philosopher oh
yeah i agree with you i kind of think
that way
and then also in in this introspective
way in your actual experience like
you when when you're writing a book for
example um
zen in the art consciousness which is
all about consciousness um you look at
the question
from the perspective of a practitioner
of zen meditation
and from that that experiential way so
the first question and i think this is
something that we all struggle with just
when we're trying to think about the
world is how do you balance those three
perspectives when you're looking at
something like consciousness for example
how do you balance how do those three
things interrelate
i've forgotten what the three are um
zen um no the site the scientific
perspective
um the the philosophical let's say
philosophical inverted commerce
perspective
and the introspective experiential
perspective oh that's easy
now you've explained um
it's all it's all about curiosity i mean
it's all
about i don't understand what is this
you obviously have seen zen and the art
of consciousness which
yeah it's kind of about consciousness
but it's it's a book of it was
originally called ten zen questions and
it was me
just writing about my experience with
ten cohan's
in zen these weird questions um and
a lot of them are basically
philosophical questions who am i
what is this i mean what is this in zen
is the fundamental question and i can
sit here and think
here's a desk um here's you know my
hands um
there's the trees blowing in the cold
wind it's the first
really cold day of the autumn now um
what's that got to do with with this
brain and anyway what
is it i mean what is the universe made
of physics will tell us it's made of
um atoms and subatomic particles and
what have you
psychologists or mystics will say it's
all mind
dualism has to be false in my opinion
and many people's opinions
but how can this mental and physical be
the same thing
they've got to be but i don't know what
it is so i'll say of an evening
smoking a joint usually and thinking
what is this
how can it be and sometimes in deep
meditation
or with psychedelics uh particularly in
deep meditation
i meditate every day i've done for
decades
i can get to the point where it's
obvious i know that i know why and how
monism is true um but then i
you know come round into a normal state
if there's such a thing
and i can't make that into a scientific
theory
but uh at the risk of rambling on at
great length
the answer to your question is they are
all really
hovering around these deep questions
about what on earth is
being alive being aware of this
immediate experience and
is there a now or you know i mean how
deluded are we i'm sure we're deluded
about consciousness and free will
but are we deluded about time and you
know i mean
yeah it's all it's all part of that and
if that questioning
through having weird experiences um
takes me to a scientific question well
i'll have a scientific go at it as i did
in several decades of doing
parapsychology and looking in vain for
paranormal phenomena
or if it takes me to a philosophical
direction like at the moment i'm arguing
deep deep long months and months of
arguing back and forth with dan dennett
about free will
then you know i like he you know he
knows i'm not a philosopher
but he's uh it's wonderful he keeps he
replies the next day or within a few
hours and then it's a week when i
kind of digest this difficult answer and
have a go so you know i'm just taken in
whichever direction by
by where this curiosity takes me i
suppose
it's interesting um it's interesting you
bring up weed
because one of the things i was
wondering is
in like in altered states um often
in fact i think you said um in one of
your talks or possibly elsewhere
that when you had your first out body
experience you felt like
the experience you were having was
realer than real and i've been
i've been one of the things that
concerns me about psychedelics is the
possibility of breaking your brain
and believing something to be true
because some kind of
and obviously i don't really know how
brains work very well but some sort of
truth
chemical is released in your brain that
makes you think things are true
that aren't true luckily it hasn't
happened yet but it's always like a
concern and i wonder how you
how you think about those moments where
things feel true
and then what you do with those feelings
like is that maybe that's what people
call gnosis
that sort of feeling of truth yeah and
the numinous
um yes that feeling that now i know
now it's right so i i don't know about
frying your brain or whatever you called
it
um i would say it's not a particular
chemical it's a particular part of the
brain that's um
that's giving the sense of ripeness and
that's going to be active
and so on of course there are some
people
actually many that's why you and i are
skeptics i guess who will take some
experience like that it might be a
dramatic psychedelic experience it might
be a very ordinary experience like
reading some
rubbish fake news um conspiracy theory
thing and going yes that fits with
everything i've always thought so it's
obviously true and i'm going to you know
tell everybody about it
um but that's not my approach obviously
so
in that out of body experience and it's
50 years ago now so
i mean i can still remember it's so
vivid but
i can't rely on my memory really but
i i would say that my response to that
was to be completely convinced
by the way it felt people having nds and
ob
is not so much ordinary obs some of them
and some not
but nds typically it's realer than real
and this may well be because at least
this is an idea that um
an ayahuasca a man i know who
who's an expert ayahuasca he wouldn't
call himself a shaitan but
he is really but he's pointed out that
um in in the many of those states you've
got no sensory input which we know is
important for having out of body and
near-death experiences
but all you've got to go on is the stuff
coming in imagination
and it's going to seem real because
there's nothing else saying it isn't
real it's a very obvious point really
but it
got out to me so it's not surprising
this this realness
but that's slightly different from the
numinous the the the
the knowing um feeling my response
in 50 years ago was to say well now i
know
i'm superior i know that there's more in
your philosophy than
all that stuff you know um and i know
that there's another world because i've
been there
and i know there's an astral body
because i have seen it and felt it and
flown around with it and so i know
so i am going to prove to the world
particularly to my
physiology and psychology lecturers at
oxford who are very
you know close-minded materialist and
i'm going to prove to them that they're
all
wrong and of course this is not a very
scientific attitude but
somehow being me whatever that means i
i was really persistent and i just went
on and on and on looking for paranormal
phenomena and never finding them
and then changing my whole question
that's really the key
to being a scientist i don't know about
a philosopher probably the same
you ask some question and if you get an
answer great
if you find that it's the wrong question
that's is as helpful in another way
because it's the questions that you ask
that are important
so i began asking well why and how do
people have realer than real feeling out
of body experiences if it's not proof of
another world and life after death and
ghosts and poltergeists and
telepathy and all the things i thought
it was and that's that's where it took
me
and that's already from the beginning a
combination of
a scientific approach and respecting the
actual experiences that you've had
and when something feels that sense of
absolute knowledge well
hold it it might be absolute knowledge
and absolutely right and really helpful
or it might be just
you know just your brain telling you
telling you wrong
that's the world we live in that's our
kind of way our minds are so yeah let's
go for it and explore
so you used the word um monas monist
earlier
and i kind of like i've got these three
m words um materialist modest
and mystic floating in my around in my
head when i think of you
do like in one of those sort of
something you write on a name label and
whereabouts
or all three that is such a pertinent
question this week
um i don't know if you know john hogan
he was
famous for um writing a book called the
end of science he he write he does a
podcast for scientific american and
um column and stuff for scientific
american
and he interviewed me a couple of weeks
ago
and wrote this whole um no it's not a
podcast sorry it's a vlogblog
wrote his scientific american blog post
about me
and we talked about these kinds of
things in a way
um and then he sent me and said here's
the link i checked all the text and
everything
and then he sent me the link and it said
at the top how to be
a mystical monitor that's a mystical
materialist
right and i went
and you know as much as you can in email
and um
immediately how could you say this and
i looked through the what i'd what he
put of what i said and
two places in that interview i've said
materialism
fails it can't account for consciousness
at least not consciousness in the way
most people think of it
idealism fails for the opposite reason
um i'm not a materialist i keep telling
everybody i'm not a materialist
sorry i shouldn't chat um and so very
kindly
because i reacted very quickly and had
time to do it it was changed to
how to be a mystical skeptic
so you can see this little you know
debate between us was very pertinent to
this moment
obviously a psychic phenomenon that you
asked that question
uh i think monist is people don't people
on a lot of people know what dual
dualist is but they don't kind of notice
the opposite which is modest and i just
call myself a neutral modest
and if i look that up online i get
completely freaked out by all the clever
and difficult things it means
um and i'm not a philosopher so i feel
all embarrassed and i don't know
so i just mean all i mean is i i'm damn
sure there's only one kind of stuff here
but i don't know what it is
when you say materialism fails to
explain consciousness
like what's what's the key failure that
you see there
well if by consciousness you mean
subjective experience that is an
experience that
i am having and is private
and nobody else can get into it
and it is um uh
different from the physical world that
we know from all the experiments and
physics and chemistry and everything
then you've got you you get very quickly
into dualism
and um i was for a long time
i mean or yeah have been a great fan of
dan dennett because he demolishes
you know he's his his version of
illusionism it's different from mine in
consciousness
but all the ways in which we get it
wrong
and um we get it wrong right from the
start really
i feel that um if you take that view on
consciousness then
then you're inevitably dragged into
dualism and that won't work
so what do you do to me the only way to
to to square any kind of materialism
with
the existence of this experience
is um by
exploring how and why we're deluded
about its nature
so i would say even i mentioned dan
dennett because
he he has this idea about cartesian
materialism
that is the idea that most philosophers
and scientists
will say no i'm not a cartesian dualist
i've given up you know substance dualism
and what have you
um and yet they still write and talk as
though
there's an audience in the cartesian
theater this mythical place inside our
heads where i
am you know and if i am as he would put
it a benign user illusion
as i would put it down malign user
illusion that
brings us to suffering and so on um
then you know what of consciousness the
the sense of
the idea that so many scientists in in
the world of consciousness studies
say well you can't have experience
without an experiencer
and i go you can you know it's
it's not how it normally is but you can
deep meditation psychedelics
there's stuff happening but there's no
one it's happening to you know this is
described by many people and myself um
so um to come back to your question
about
why materialism fails it either takes
you into dualism
like that or it puts you straight into
the
problems of physics and you know what
what does materialism mean anyway what
is it all made of you know in any way we
we only know the physics by doing
experiments which we have experience of
reading off the numbers on the
dials and there well you can see i'm
getting into
i'll shut up because i'm getting myself
into the sort of trouble that i like but
i can't say anything go here and
well let me move you into even more um
troublesome
area uh let's talk about um
let's talk about you know esoteric stuff
um so
there's a couple of things which like
from you know my lay person's
understanding
seem to be sort of groping at a
conception of how culture works
or what we might call mimetics but in a
weird way so there's like
jungian archetypes and i don't know if
you're familiar with chaos magic at all
but they
they're sort of looking at it's
basically the idea that there is um
what alan moore calls uh like an ideal
world or idea realm
and they think that they can intervene
in it so they basically think they can
control
the way that ideas flow around it by
doing all sorts of rituals and
that's like platonic sort of it's kind
of platonic yeah it's kind of inspired
by that
but i'm sure you're familiar with
jungian archetypes so
do you think there are connections
between mimetics
and that sort of thing are these like
the alchemy that will become the science
or are they completely divorced and i'm
barking up the wrong tree or what do you
think
i'm just smiling because i did a really
weird and stressful interview with
jordan peterson somebody's nodding
um he said medics is rubbish it's all
just jungian archetypes
and no it isn't but it was so
so slippery to argue with that you know
we never got anywhere with that but um
you can watch that online it's on my
website if anyone's interested
because he's quite a a strong
interesting character
um so uh
i i don't really think those kind of
ideas make sense
um i would say rather that
human brains are pretty much similar
the world over of course every brain is
sculpted differently by
upbringing by the memes that you um
are forced on you when you're young and
then that you select as you get older
and become
more able to select the memes that you
want to keep and the ones you want to
pass on
and so on um but it's not like there
it's not like the the memes themselves
hang on i must say for anyone who's not
aware of the
what i mean by the word meme i'm using
its original sense from dawkins
that which is imitated or that which is
copied so if somebody copies an idea of
painting in this way or an idea of a
joke or you know
it's the it's the idea or the behavior
or whatever is copied is what i call the
meme
don't worry about where it is in the
brain or any other
complications just just that so um
you could see how you'd get to the idea
that well they're all kind of out there
already and
why and and what would that where would
they be what would be them
the medium in which they're carried i
mean information has to have a
have a a physical basis to to be
information it can't just go float as
far as i know
can't just go floating about you know
you catch it
so these similarities and that would
apply to the archetypes which
in one reading of jung um
they're sort of out there and weird in
their psychic synchronicity and all of
that in another reading of it it's just
how we evolved and
no wonder we're similar and we come up
with these architects again because of
our similar brains
um so and the same i would say about
having outer body experiences and so on
it doesn't prove there's an astral body
that goes somewhere else
it shows that everyone around the world
is capable of having this dislocation of
body schema
and it's our similar brains that do it
so no i i
i don't go in the direction of of those
ideas no
that makes sense to me too i i think
like i said perhaps
perhaps some of these things are trying
to to look for explanations and using
like more metaphorical thinking as they
try to
explore it and come up with some strange
conclusions but interesting conclusions
yeah good to have a lot of ideas to
choose from when you're out exactly
yeah um so the other thing that i i
mentioned that i wanted to ask you about
was this idea um that a lot of people
have been talking about around here in
the star
um that we are as you know the sea of
faith recedes and we become a less
religious
culture worldwide and i don't even know
if that's true to be honest i don't have
stats to hand but it's
you know generally accepted that
religion's on the wane come true
in most western countries and certainly
in europe but it's
it's dodgy elsewhere that's exactly what
popped into my head as i was saying that
i was like
be careful check myself but anyway so
this idea that without the religious
sort of structures that we used to have
um that gave us meaning um whatever that
means
that people are feeling a deficit and
that's coming across in you know
this longing for the interest in
meditation
interest in philosophy and on the bad
side you know like nihilism
and what people some people have called
a mental health crisis again
don't have statistics but it's an
interesting observation
i just wanted as someone who's an
atheist was obviously is concerned about
these big questions
what you make of that do you think that
to talk about the idea of a meaning
crisis even makes sense
and what would you suggest would be
solutions if you do
i suspect that it's not i don't know
what you mean by meaning exactly but i
suspect it's not so much meaning as
purpose
it's the feeling of purposelessness that
gets people down
and christianity um gives you a purpose
um because you know obeying god's will
so does islam
obeying allah and only doing things that
allah wishes and so on
gives you a purpose and a structure and
we humans need structure however ghastly
the structure i mean it horrifies me
i consider them major religions to be
really pernicious memeplexes if you look
at the history of
any of them you find you know it's like
an evolutionary
bush of of different sects and so on
and you ask the memetic question the
question coming from a meme's
perspective memes are revolving and
competing to use our brains to get
copied
coming from that perspective why has
islam ended up this way
most of it with the you know the sheer
and the sunnis and the different bits
there are
and christianity and these multiple
versions but loads more died out
that's a kind of evolutionary
perspective well the ones that stay
one of the big reasons is basic biology
you know
um the the basic thing about sperm and
eggs
um the best biological strategy for
women is to protect
their um that the few children they can
have choose the best mate they can and
and look look after them best they can
uh the best strategy for men is to
everything in sight and it doesn't
matter because you don't have as many
children and let the women look after
them
and what do we find in these religions
what we find
is women trap them from sorry from the
man's point of view
yeah but but if you're going to if you
if you're a man you're going to put any
investment into a woman and
those children then you've got to make
sure that they're your children and not
somebody else's
hence veils and
body coverings and all the admonitions
against sex and all of that kind of
thing
those kind of things it's it's just
basic biology
meaning that these memes thrive better
than nicer memes as from a woman's point
of view
um so we have all these religions around
um
i take buddhism which i i mean although
i've been training in zen for
40 years nearly um i'm not a buddhist i
don't want to sign up to any beliefs
obviously
i wouldn't would i um but the training
is amazing
but a fascinating phenomenon that i
think has happened in buddhism and i'd
like to explore more is
what the buddha said mostly is about
the self is an illusion everything is
ephemeral
and ever-changing um
that's well it is impermanent it has all
the marks
of existence um impermanent suffering um
it can lead to nihilism and that is one
of the problems i mean
that you mentioned nihilism it can lead
you to oh i don't exist what's the point
of anything
or it can lead you to deep insight into
business and how it is and being able to
behave and watch thoughts come and go
and self come and go and so on but
what's happening in buddhism
is is it is a harping back to all the
ideas
of reincarnation which were around in
some of the countries where buddhism
went in the early time
because reincarnation gives you that
purpose if you're really good in this
life and you do lots of meditation and
so on that
ah you will get to a higher bit you'll
be next next life will be as a higher
being
and if you're really bad and wicked
you'll come back as i don't know
whatever i'm low in the low hells
and then all these hells and things
which don't to me make any sense
whatsoever
so i like zen because it's more free of
those things than other
kinds of um of buddhism so we see the
memetic processes here
turning giving people purposes in life
that then cause them to take on
absolutely untrue rubbish ideas like
there's a heaven and a hell
and there's a god who cares about you
and all of that kind kind of stuff
now i've completely lost the plot what
your question was
no i think you you've given it's
interesting because this is kind of what
you do
um when when talking about consciousness
as well in that you
um you say the questions that we're
asking are the wrong questions
um like we can't find consciousness
because
it's not that's fine and i feel like
you're saying a similar thing about
meaning
there's a lot of talk about realizing
meaning whether that means um
people think the meanings out there in
the world in in a religion or in a
transcendent deity or whatever
and that they're going to realize it and
find out it's true or realizing it as in
making it real like kind of an
existentialist thing if make it real
um and what i what i got from what you
were saying or what i feel like was
underneath what you were saying is
perhaps the answer is
to live with the reality that there is
no meaning
and find a way to be in that instead of
searching for it or trying to invent it
yes i think that's right i think the
can't think of the right adjective way
to live
fill in blank space um is to accept that
all meanings and purposes
are created by us and by our culture and
by our memes
and find a way in life
to go with those meanings and those
purposes without thinking that there's
anything ultimate about them
or anything that will lead to something
beyond the life that you're living with
these
temporarily held meanings and purposes
yeah that's great i got some i got some
self-help advice as well
some of you
so i suppose it's time for me to stop
being so shellfish and share susan with
all of you
um if people have put questions in the
chat
but i they haven't put whether they
would like to speak or whether they
would like me to speak on their behalf
so um that would that would be useful if
you could just say
um this is a question i'd like to ask or
whether it's a question that i'd like to
ask on your behalf
they don't indicate anything that means
they'll uh happy to ask
themselves oh okay cool well in that
case
uh can we um call on tom tom beakbain
uh if you're ready to ask your question
that'd be great
oh hi susan i'm tom bigbang from toronto
uh since you wrote the meme machine um
do you think there's been progress
towards
unifying uh different viewpoints you
know
the materialistic viewpoint and and the
mystical viewpoint
uh are you becoming less skeptical or
um more skeptical about um
science's ability to sort of explain
the the soft side of life if you like oh
i'm endlessly optimistic about the
ability of science because science is
not
it's not a fixed thing that you can pin
down it's more of an attitude and
approach
so whatever problem or question there is
we may not be able to do the science on
it right now but in principle
i this is a dodgy one isn't it but in
principle i don't see that there's
anything that science can't actually
uh get a handle on i'm not sure why
why you relate this to the me machine
because i thought maybe you were going
in the direction of has there been any
progress in mimetics
which has been extremely little and then
lots of interesting reasons
possible reasons why um but
i don't think there's any reason to
think that science
can't have a go at it just that we
haven't found the right way
i i could draw an analogy it's only an
analogy
with with darwin and and um
the recognition of evolution by natural
selection
that just hung on in there i mean people
at the time
saw some of the potential were horrified
a lot of them were horrified
um some thought it was wonderful but in
the absence of the science to be able to
discover genetics um it couldn't get
very far without knowing
without knowing how the copy you need
for an evolutionary process
copying varying and selecting you need
those three to make up the evolutionary
algorithm
and although darwin could see that he
didn't know about the term algorithm but
that's basically what he was saying that
if you keep doing that again and again
and again you must get
evolution but without knowing how the
copying was done
um you know how the selection was done
natural selection because things die if
there's not enough food and there's
predators and there's not enough water
and air you know
naturally natural selection does the job
but he couldn't understand
uh the the nature of the copying of the
information down the generations
or the where the variation came from
and without that couldn't really get
anywhere until the early 20th century
when it became scientifically available
through the kind of um
biology chemistry and so on that we had
and i think it's the same with mimetics
um we we're floundering around i i still
think i mean i read i read the mean
machine again recently because it's 20
years and i thought oh
god what did i write um
and i think i would still agree with
most of it certainly
the basic argument but i think we're not
in a position at the moment
to um to write to ask a sort of
questions that give us a scientific
handle on it
but i think we might be getting there i
hope so and i certainly don't think
there's any reason why we shouldn't
does that answer your question yes
good great um peter would you like to
ask your question
yeah um so you mentioned this on your uh
the answer to the
last question um so i was curious what
your sense of how the field of medics
has progressed and you said very little
so maybe why is that the case you think
and then the other part of the question
is what is the best criticism
of the concept or the field you have
heard or any criticism that given you
pause
i i think there are lots of reasons why
i think basically it hasn't got anywhere
what what has happened
since in in those 20 years i mean the
the meme idea goes back to 1976 with
dawkins
selfish gene um but if you start from
the mean machine
um basically most scientists think the
idea is rubbish
remember that 20 years ago there was no
such thing as an internet meme
so most people now only know the term
meme
through the existence of internet memes
which made richard pretty
pissed off to begin with and me in a way
but i'm more than he argued that
actually they're a very good example
if you if you know what an internet meme
is then you can easily grasp the idea
that
memes are information that's copied
buried and selected and there's huge
selection pressure to the very few
beautiful pussycats that get on you know
get millions of views and the
not so attractive pussycats that or
worse jokes that don't
so i think they're not a bad example so
that's been
very good in the sense that the term
meme has come to be much better known
um but what has happened simultaneously
is a real flourishing of cultural
evolution theory
and and and empirical research
so i have been to some conferences um
and
met with people who are studying for
example
in inuit by inuits and the way that's
passed on
and the selection is when they sink you
know um
use that as a very sort of simple idea
of memes
meme selection um but they they study uh
apprenticeships and and groups of
different
different societies it's a lot of it is
anthropology
and the basic difference i would say
between and it's very successful is a
lot of work going on
really discovering a lot about human
behavior in many different cultures
um now the real difference between that
and mimetics is absolutely fundamental
in the end those people
go back to genetic advantage as the
driving force
so the reason why the cultures evolved
the way they do and the behaviors it
evolved the way they did is because
of the way the genes have made us
and that it ultimately benefits the
genes this goes back to um you know
wilson's
the uh famous uh saying that um
the genes will always keep culture on a
leash
now there are many of these people will
say well obviously the leash is getting
longer and longer
we live now everything changes so fast
the genes haven't got time to kill off
those of us who believe the wrong idea i
mean
you know it's all happening too fast but
the memetic idea of course
is is quite different it is that memes
are a second replicator
this planet has genes first memes second
a new way of copying information
using brains not using dna and chemistry
um and that just as genes are selfish
so memes are selfish and that culture is
evolving
for the benefit of the memes now why
hasn't this gone anywhere
well i would just like to mention one
recent study which is absolutely
fascinating
um a study of um the witch trials
and you know burning which is at stake
and all those horrible things
um a study which showed um
that this is not really science it's
more um history but
it showed that if if the um
if you analyze um
the effects of these witch trials were
they of benefit to the
people who were burnt no were they of
benefit to people doing the burning
no i mean there's a deep analysis in
this paper
um uh is it a benefit to the society a
whole as whole
which it happened is it of benefit to
any small groups within that society
and all the answers came back to be no
and that i think is an example of the
way we need to go in mimetics
to find something where we can show that
it benefited those memes
without benefiting us the mean machines
i'd love it to go if you want to know
more about
why it doesn't partly i've i've said
because it's difficult
to find ways to do that but i'm sure
we're beginning to do it and i'm sure we
will
but people also just don't get the idea
i think the main reason
is people don't get it and they partly
don't get it because they don't like it
um but they partly don't get it because
the same problem that darwin had it and
they say
oh do you know my mp is a creationist
um but sorry this is kind i can you
believe it
21st century my employees anyway
yeah here in south devon yes he
represents me
in parliament he's very nice and
charming and always answers my
objection emails i write him but anyway
now where was i um so
i was thinking i'm thinking of the amer
americans more than
um 50 percent of americans don't believe
in evolution
the reason i think the fundamental
reason
is the way we naturally think is that
design records
buses here had to have a designer uh
this
phone had to have a designer uh this cup
had to have a designer and that's kind
of true
in a sense there were humans involved in
this and they had the
ideas and then you know so the idea of
design without a designer is
counterintuitive and that was absolutely
what
dawkins was on about and what den it was
on about but it's counterintuitive
and i think that is one reason why
people don't like
mimetics and another reason is they
don't like applying evolutionary theory
at all so sociologists and so on don't
like
um the the sort of biological
implications of evolutionary theory
coming in
the biologists don't like people like me
because well i don't know anyway they
don't like the idea of
of of um evolutionary theory being kind
of subverted to
medics when that's kind of weird and
that's their realm and shouldn't be
taken away
many many reasons why it's difficult i
think mimetics will only thrive
when and if it proves possible to carry
on that kind of idea of experiments in
which you find out
is this to the benefit of the genes is
it to benefit of the humans is it to the
benefit of
groups or is it actually just only to
the benefit of the means
that would make mimetics different from
standard cultural evolution theory
and very very much worth doing
wow good question um we've got another
one from someone with a very appropriate
um
handle uh would mimetic caper like to
ask that question
or would you like me to ask it for you i
can ask it great
hi susan so um here's my question a
cartesian dualism
destroys purpose by making the objective
world void of it
and the subjective world undefinable
but if purpose or desire is memetic
is there a way to bridge the cartesian
gap through the scientific study of
memes
as a means of re-emerging the world in
meaning
you're going to have to repeat that
slowly because i don't
i didn't understand the first bit so
just say that again
so the first bit i'm making the claim
that uh cartesian dualism
um voids
uh people's world view of meaning
because
um the objective world is just clockwork
it's just happening automatically
there's no
uh purpose to it it's just it's random
or
uh i i'm with you in the subjective
world we can't say anything about
because it's not observable
that's very interesting i mean i didn't
understand it because i i
don't agree at all but i now you've said
it again i can see what you're getting
at
but i really don't see why cartesian
dualism should do that because
i mean after all cartesian dualism gives
we humans
and not the rest of the living world a
soul or a spirit
which answers to god and therefore
there's huge purpose i mean the purpose
of a true cartesian dualist as in
they cuts time certainly but probably
still to some extent to this day and
that's i think why it's so popular i
mean
basically some form of dualism is the
natural way we think
we know from developmental psychology
that kids from a very young age
uh and i've got two little
granddaughters aged two and five and i
can see these things emerging
as the sense of self emerges um so
comes the sense of and and also the
discrimination between
living and non-living things self-moving
and things that have to be pushed
these things all lay the ground for a
kind of dualism in which there are minds
that
do things and design things and have
ideas and there are physical things out
there that
we manipulate it's the world that given
to us um to manipulate
and so i think so to my mind that kind
of dualism
gives people um basic meaning
and purpose in life their purpose is to
be a good soul and
and to exploit the world the best they
can
um rather than taking it away i can
imagine from what you've said that for
some people it would take away meaning
and purpose but i think
for the majority it doesn't so what's
the second part of your question
well i i guess i could have said uh you
could replace
cartesian dualism in my question with
scientific materialism because
yeah i know it's just so much yeah
absolutely straight on there that will
take you
in a certain interpretation that will
take you straight into it yes
yeah so go on yeah so the second part of
the question
is that uh if purpose or desire or
meaning
whatever you want to call it a if it's
memetic
is there a way to bridge the cartesian
gap
through the scientific study of means as
a way of
re-emerging the world in meaning like
can um
because there's purpose in the memes
i guess is what i'm saying um
studying the meme scientifically it
brings purpose back to the world
i am not at all sure about that because
there's so little
of real scientific study of memes but i
want to
to to think about your suggestion that
that purpose and meaning in life are
mimetic
so the specific purposes that we have
for example
i get up in the morning and get to my
desk and there's that bloody email
completion i can't bear it and i have to
spend however much time it is um trying
to deal with it and that's a kind of a
purpose that's a nomadic purpose
because that's all memes all that
information
being sent to me um
i can have other purposes for example
like to be
as mindful as my training
allows me to be and that
living from just going along responding
thoughtlessly to to everything and so
and that's a meme that i have been
taught
um over the decades how to
um in zen terms sit down shut up and see
what the mind does
um so those are memes but fundamentally
we go back to genes and this is so often
the case there are pure memetic things
we can do
people studying stuff on the internet
there's lots and lots of that there's
lots of fantastic studies
of um of mimetics um in the digital
world
which i think is a somewhat different
issue but when it comes to
memes um shared with humans
the need for purpose the need for
meaning is a biological
drive i would say we
we wouldn't we wouldn't be here as a
species if we didn't have
genes that inclined us to seek out
purposes
and and follow them up and they start
obviously with getting food
getting mates having fun um learning
stuff that might be useful to us i mean
that genetic endowment has given us the
basis
from which all of these this yearning
for purpose and meaning comes
the memes just come in and give answers
to some extent so i would never say that
purpose of meaning is purely memetic
would i never say that well i don't at
the moment anyway
so i just want to add on the one last
part of my question that
it's a separate question are you
familiar with rene gerard
no i'm afraid not so i'm gonna strongly
recommend
that um you do at least some
investigation into this guy because he's
uh
he's a i guess he's a literary uh
theorist
anthropologist i'm not maybe a bit of
both um but his full
theory is based on uh imitated desire
um and he actually calls it
the neck desire but it's like the latin
word pneumatic it's basically the same
meaning
um and you know i think
mimetic are not the same but anyway go
on
oh okay well um
yeah he probably exaggerates the degree
to which
all purpose is imitated or
all desire like he he um i definitely
think there's something to the
biological
uh causation of desire right but
um gerard doesn't focus on that because
he's it's not really in
his uh domain but he's a very
interesting theorist
um i've written down the name yeah
yeah i i second that recommendation for
rene gerard i've read a lot it's
interesting especially as an atheist to
read him because i believe he's a
christian and it comes from that
perspective
but uh yeah it's definitely worth a read
so um
maybe evan could go next if you're ready
to ask your question
will i just say something about that i
think that's not incompatible with what
i was saying that
you start with a biological um
foundation of
wanting desires and um of wanting um
yeah desires and purpose and and all of
that and the memes build on that
they wouldn't be doing what they're
doing if it weren't for that biological
underpinning but studying the way
they're then
um imitated and copied is
i guess i will have a look and read this
stuff
um evan if you want to step forward sure
so to speak
hi this is evan thank you for coming
here i've
followed and loved your work for a long
time i was had a question i'm
assuming in this question that you're
familiar with uh thomas metzinger's
ideas
um like has presented a being no one for
example i was curious just if you had
any commentary on that or because to me
that seems like an extremely satisfying
theory his whole phenomenal self-model
theory about the nature of cells and how
you know a sort of materialist
compatible theory for how cells get
constructed i was wondering if you had
any thoughts or comments on that
before i try and answer that let me tell
you a story
i had this very dramatic outer body
experience in 1970.
in 1985 my husband got a job in germany
and now this is pre-internet pre-mobile
phones everything letters and so on so
on
i got a letter from this young man we
were both
young in 1985 called thomas metzinger
saying because he'd read my book on out
of body experiences which is a very
skeptical book
in 1982 and he wrote and he said
um you are wrong i've had an out-of-body
experience and i know we're going back
to rebecca your question about
knowing he knew that there's life after
death and a natural world and all that
stuff and he wanted to
prove to me that i was wrong and i said
well actually i'm now
living in germany and so he came to
visit me in tubingen
and we just got on like a house on fire
and that's a
question isn't it i don't know i don't
know if it's just an english expression
we got on very well
and we've been friends ever since i
don't see him very often but
he's in germany and i'm here um but
i've known him very well so i was very
very interested in that
that book about self it's very good
to answer your question properly i would
need to read it again
um i think the uh the the whole self
model thing
it's going back that long even in 1986 i
gave a conference paper
in which i said that um
there's nothing it's like to be a human
being the whole thing
there's only something it's like to be
the model the representation
and in a way that's what he's saying
but his way of saying it is slightly
different from mine but
the reason that i stopped doing that
after 1986 is because i
simply couldn't get a handle on what's
meant by a model or a representation
and i looked into the philosophy a
little bit again no internet
um you know have to go to the university
library and go to philosophy books and
fight you know it's really really hard
to find things out in those days
um and um
i gave up on it because i really
couldn't at all
make a theory out of what's meant by
model now i'm not saying that his theory
falls because of that same problem but
it's still lurking there this
self model and its um implications for
subjectivity
what exactly is the model do we need to
know
inside the brain what the model is doing
this also relates to
meditation practice like myself thomas
is a long-term lifelong
and we have shared many discussions
about that as well
um so
i i'm very much in tune with with
thomas's views
but i wouldn't go oh he's absolutely
right because i don't think we've
we've got to the bottom of what it means
to be a phenomenal self-model
and i think we may do so and that will
throw much more
light on both his views and mine and
doughnuts and various other people who
talk about these models
there's a little connection here with
the outer body experience stuff because
i did a book a couple of years ago
called seeing myself in which i really
pulled together
what happened to me in that original
experience all that time ago
which led me to think i was going to
prove the existence of you know all that
stuff
um which is that we now know that
the the temporary parietal junction
here is a kind of hub
for controlling their body schema which
is a model or representation of the body
that you need all the time to be able to
move and speak and everything
else and that autobody experiences
happen when that's disturbed
that that model of self is then
connected up in different parts of the
brain with a self-image who am i what am
i like what do people think of me what
do i think of myself
and to the control areas and frontal
cortex and so on
um now knowing that kind of stuff
um maybe we can the body schemer is a
really
easy philosophically i guess easy idea
of a model it literally represents the
position of the body in a
three-dimensional space
but a model a phenomenal self-model is
something slight somewhat more than that
and i would love to know the connections
so yes uh i'm absolutely um
i love thomas's ideas but there's i
think there's a long way to go
great these are all such great questions
i'm glad i passed it over to the chat
um so maybe we can squeeze in just one
more uh
we've um adam has got a popular question
that people seem to want him to step
forward and ask if you'd like to come
forward adam hi
um i was just wondering about the moral
status of the conf
potential conflict between genes and
memes
because like if you have both
replicators going it you know
i could almost imagine a future in the
memoirs where some humans are fighting
on behalf of the memes
other humans that want the genes to
control what happens i mean
it just it makes me wonder if we're
stuck as atheists in a kind of morally
neutral landscape there of like well
there's genes and memes and like those
both seem like meaningful processes but
like
is there is it just sort of a a watch
like are they just
you know two political parties or you
know oh that's so depressing why do we
have to have such a depressing question
because where you're taking excuse me
where you're taking me of course is is
what you're hinting at there
you kind of you you ask the question as
though will it end up like that it's
there already
people defend the memes they have and i
would love to understand
more why that is i mean you can glibly
say well cognitive dissonance once
you've believed something
you don't want the dissonance of then
discovering it's wrong
and of course we're back to what it
means to be a scientist or a
philosopher who's changes your mind when
the evidence makes you change it and so
on
but religions going back to them and you
were talking about atheism
our prime example of uh me of memplexes
that cause their bearers to pass them on
and therefore all those american
christians well and
all those all the muslims around the
world not all
lots of them the ones who are deeply
infected with it
um they are willing to spend a huge
proportion of their
time and energy um and brain power
to force those ideas on other people
why why and we're back then to my
question about
which religions or which religious um
uh versions have thrived
take spread the good news of jesus
now biologically we are a
social species we use reciprocal
altruism
um you know i do something for you you
pay me back we keep tracks on who's good
and who's not
so from that point of view we all want
to be good or at least we want to be
perceived
to be good and i call this the goodness
trick or the altruism trick
so these religions play a trick it's
it's evolved through other religions
dying out the ones
to some extent the ones left certainly
in those major religions
are the ones that that tell you you are
a good person if you pass on these ideas
so um in islam there's a kind of
conflict because in some places in the
quran it says you must never force it on
anyone but then in other places it's
telling you how important it is that
everybody else joins you and otherwise
you're going to kill them
or or um various other horrible
punishments for them
um so that's a good example of
how um people come
to want to promote their ideas i mean
two examples a simple one just the kind
of cognitive dissonance i've had this
great idea so i want other people to
agree with me because then i look clever
and good
um so i'm good in that way or the kind
of moral one which i think you were
getting at more
that that religions give you um
a rule about what counts as moral and
what counts as not moral so i'm sure
all of you whichever of you out there
are atheists will have thought about
this because
constantly we're being told um that
the people many religious people
feel that you can't have more you can't
have good morals
without believing in god because they
all come from god and this is
very pernicious but it's part of the way
those religions have succeeded
is to persuade the believers that that's
how it is that they wouldn't be good
if they didn't follow these rules and
then the rules of course were back again
and something else you said reminded me
we're back again into that biological
thing the big sex difference thing which
is
obviously particularly up some to me as
a
female is
is is um it's very often the women
it's the women who actually carry out
the fgm it's women who persuade other
women that
abortion is a bad idea and there are the
american situation with the uh
the woman who's just died and we might
get an anti-abortion
um lawyer chosen by trump
the these are examples it really that's
definitely a really horrible example to
think that
women will will um
stand up for those biologically based
ideas that every life is precious that
it's got a soul given by god
even a even a few cells in a
um have have been beginning to be an
embryo
um have more importance than a mother's
life
or indeed the child's life that might be
horrendous if the child wasn't wanted
um i i find myself going how can this be
the moment the answer is there those
religions have
evolved in ways that keep those things
um going
for biological reasons and i i
in my more optimistic moments i see we
are moving away from that
in the uk now more than half people
say they have no religion um that's not
mean they're all atheists but they have
no religious affiliation
um and and and then i'm very optimistic
and then i watch what's happening
in the islamic world and what's
happening in the united states of
america
and i sometimes despair i don't want to
end up and i'm a horrible miserable like
didn't anyone say anything more cheerful
than
get me out of that um
i don't know whether it's a more
cheerful um thought
but um i thought it might make sense to
end with a quick
a quick note on teams which we haven't
touched on at all
yet and like the future of me the third
replicator what are we to expect
but maybe that's that's more depressing
stuff i don't know no it's not
depressing it well it's kind of
frightening but that's different from
depressing
uh i guess i have to be fairly brief um
we did touch on it in a sense
when talking about um internet memes
um i some years ago now
i i started wondering whether
all the memes that come because more and
more in my life going from
as i've described you know within
writing letters to to
to email and and podcasts and all of
this
um is this just more memes or is there
something fundamentally
oh it must be six o'clock look what is
about to arrive
thank you oh lovely i expect mine to
arrive soon too
thank you very much my love takes away
the teacup and brings me the wine
um so um i began ask i'll have a sip if
you don't mind
oh please do cheers
and then the awful six o'clock news will
be on it's it's six o'clock in the
evening i'm not it's not six o'clock
morning drinking
and the news will be on and the latest
covert disasters
um so i was asking myself is this
just more memes than they're just kind
of in the computer rather than in our
heads or is it something fundamentally
different
and the more i thought about it the more
i thought it's something fundamentally
different
and in the years since i first had this
idea this is in my
2008 ted lecture and a chapter that
started it all off
for a book um i decided that it's
fundamentally different
i'll explain why i'll try to be do it
briefly but
i thought well how did the second
replicator
appear in the first place what happened
was
the phenotypes constructed by the genes
in other words
animals plants and human bodies um
began to copy information in a new way
so there was the only evolutionary
process was chemical copying of dna and
rna and so on but then
came copying of behaviors and making
noises and
the beginnings of language and all of
that so that the
the physical thing that was created by
the genes
now gave rise to a new kind of copying
so then my question was well could that
happen again
and it's a very close analogy here
always be careful of analogies
um it's a close analogy here to say that
we humans with our memes constructed
computers
and phones and servers and all of that
stuff
for our own benefit so we thought
but those machines started doing the
copying varying selecting
on their own without us and i decided
i mean not exactly arbitrarily but i
mean i felt i was alone
struggling with these ideas so it's up
to me to make a decision
and i decided that if we could show
that in the cloud which probably didn't
exist then i don't know but in
cyberspace
the machinery that we constructed is
doing those three processes
without our interference then there's a
new replicator a third replicator
i first called it teams and then people
started thinking i was talking about
football and which i absolutely wasn't
so i changed it to dreams i think
actually should have been threams
to be third replicator but try dreams i
don't know
i hoped i wrote an article in new
scientist asking people to suggest names
and i got 23 different
words and none of them hardly any
duplications at all and so anyway
so at the moment it's dreams um
and and why you're saying that this is
depressing but it's more
a bit scary rather than depressing i
think it's rather exciting but important
if i'm right about this and it is a
third replicator
then it's a selfish replicator all that
digital information all those bloody
things that come in and shout at you
you know and all those adverts saying
buy another one of those
you know shirt you bought last week and
you know
um these are evolving and proliferating
for
for their own sake selfishly and out
there if you think of things like
search engines they are combining their
their
copying varying and selecting
information and sending it out they're
going around there are
crawlers going around collecting up
stuff there's a massive amount now
which there wasn't then of what i would
call dreams
the um the machinery doing itself
this becomes a an argument about
the difference between artificial
intelligence that is distributed
and out there and self-evolving and the
kind of artificial intelligence that
most people seem to be scared of
which is something that we have created
and put into a relatively limited thing
like a robot or a computer or whatever
and you could turn it off
potentially you know you can't turn off
evolved entities if there are evolved
entities i mean my guess looking at
biological processes
evolutionary processes is that out there
in the cloud
there will be entities that collect
together um
that protect themselves because they'll
thrive better than bits of
dreams that don't get into groups same
way religions do same way biology
things do and there will be those
entities out there competing
and they'll be partly using our brains
to you know
keep going the machinery they'll be
using our resources
this is threatening to the planet
because if you think about how much
fossil fuels
are being devoted on this planet to
creating all this machinery
it's increasing very fast all the time
and just transmitting stuff backwards
and forwards
you know every email we send has a
carbon cost
and and if that is proliferating as
evolutionary processes do
then we ought to be understanding the
problems of ai
and what's happening in the world in
that way so to me it's more
a challenge to people to either show
that i'm wrong about that and it's just
a
nice idea but wrong okay well just silly
bad idea
or to start looking at whether it's
really happening
where it's happening how it's happening
and
and and try and answer the question in a
world with three replicators
what is the role of us human beings
and that's an interesting and difficult
question i'd
rather leave it there than with the
difference but it's it's it's a good one
it's a good one to have raised and it's
definitely something that i think we
should all
yeah give some thought to uh so i'm
sorry to keep you into your wine time
um i'm just going to say thank you ever
so much for answering and being so
um so gracious and paying such close
attention to what we're all asking
sometimes we're a bit muddled but
you know we're kind of in awe of you so
or at least i'll speak for myself
um i'll pass it back to peter uh he has
some announcements to make and
let me just say i've really enjoyed the
people i can see it's so nice to have
you know even a small nodding or shaking
and some lovely smile from osm bishop
and the others of you lots more nodding
thank you very much i i've enjoyed
talking to you thank you so much for
coming so i'll pass it back to peter
beautiful uh thanks rebecca for the
excellent emceeing
uh susan for coming out to the stoa and
getting a hit from questions from all
all corners um so upcoming events we got
one
coming up in less than an hour uh dave
snowden uh naturalizing sense making
he's a science major in residence
for the month of october um or september
i should say when sometime or not
october yet so that's at
2 p.m eastern time so you can rsvp there
and if you like this event we got an
event next week
uh called memes virality
and the occult with chris gabriel and he
has this youtube channel about means
where he analyzes them
that's september 28th at 6 pm eastern
time you can rsp there
we've got tons of events on the website
um
stowe.ca if you'd like to support us
while we medically
steal the culture you can do so on
patreon
um that being said again susan rebecca
everyone thank you for coming to the
store today
thank you thank you for inviting me and
causing me such